A Guide to the Papers of Henry Clay, 1798-1934, n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series I: Correspondence and Documents
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to [Henry] C. [Westervelt] 1845 September 20, ALS, 1 p.; with address cut from leaf or cover; docketed; postmarked Lexington, Ky. Sep. 21. #3193. (Box-folder 2:81)
    Clay thanks Westervelt for his letter "communicating the desire of Mr. [William] Fischerman to make and present me a pair of boots, and for that purpose, to obtain from me an old boot or some other adequate measure of the leg and foot which he kindly desires to cover." Clay fears that the old boot, "if I were to send one, might never reach its destination. It would be an inconvenient customer to the P.[ost] Office department...and if sent through any other, it might, by mistake, get upon some other leg & foot, and lead its strange companion a dance." Clay encloses [not present] a "paper measure of my leg and foot, taken by a plain but worthy boot and shoemaker in Lexn." who is, like Mr./ Fischerman "a foreigner" and "a good whig." A note below Clay's signature in an unidentified hand states "The boots were made in an elegent [sic] & comfortable manner under my superintedance [sic], with the hair (undressed inside) and were as a beautiful a specimen of the Mechanic art as I remember to have seen. Mr. Clay recd them & expressed his kind acknowledgements to Mr. Fisherman [sic] personally."
  - Henry Clay to Benjamin Belch 1845 November 20, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Lexington, Ky. Nov. 21. #2180. (Box-folder 2:82)
    Clay received Balch's letter "transmitting a plan of the National Life Insurance Company of Massachusetts." He appreciates the offer to be appointed president, but cannot "reconcile it to my sense of propriety to accept the appointment."
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to Messrs. David S. Brown, Henry White, A.I. Lewis, William Reynolds, Ch. Gibbons, Charles W. Churchman, and John E. Kean 1845 December 16, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with attached blank leaf; Barrow. #1649, Tracy W. McGregor Library. (Box-folder 2:83)
    Clay thanks the subscribers for the presentation by White of a letter and book "entitled, 'A testimonial of gratitude and affection to Henry Clay.'" He says that it is impossible "to find language of sufficient force and strength to express to you the emotions of gratitude and thankfulness excited in my breast by this precious and affecting testimonial." He is "also charged by Mrs. Clay" to present her thanks "to the Ladies and Gentlemen who have had the goodness to send her a Casket of rich jewels." He closes with warm thanks and acknowledgement to White for "performing a long journey, at a most inclement season, to fulfill the commission entrusted to him."
  - Certificate of Membership in the American Colonization Society 1846 March 16, DS, 1 p.; signed by Henry Clay. #5718. (Box-folder 2:84)
    Printed certificate, for Mrs. Emmeline Rockwell.
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to Nathan Sargent, 1846 April 28, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with detached address leaf; docketed; postmarked Lexington, Ky. Apr. 28. #991, Tracy W. McGregor Library. (Box-folder 2:85)
    Clay has returned to Ashland after an absence of four months and found Sargent's letter of March 13. He comments on the divisions in Congress and says that if Congress should "finally disagree, and leave the Oregon question where it has been so many years, I for one shall not regard it as National misfortune." Clay says he has not been "and am not now, without fears for the peace of the Country." He closes by stating that "it would be altogether premature, and highly indiscreet and impolitic for the Whig party to make any movement whatever, in favor of any body, in respect to the next Presidential election."
  - Henry Clay to Mr. and Mrs. Maury 1846 May, ANS, 1 p.; photocopy, location of original unknown. #931. (Box-folder 2:86)
    "With the best wishes for Mrs. Maury and the warmest regards for Mr. W. Maury"
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to John Wood, Jr., Hardins Tavern, Albemarle County, Va. 1846 September 10, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Lexington, Ky. Sep. 10. #10433. (Box-folder 2:87)
    Clay writes that he received Wood's friendly letter and assures him that he "never supposed that the act of wantonness, to which I called your attention, was performed by any respectable person of your community." Because of his high regard for the community, Clay "thought it due to it to transmit to you the means of discovering and exposing the guilty individual." Clay closes with warm thanks for Wood's friendship.
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to Dr. Geo[rge] McClellan 1846 September 24, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. #1754-b. (Box-folder 2:88)
    Clay has received McClellan's letter "communicating the death of my Grandson Martin Duralde." Clay thanks McClellan for his attentions and asks him to have his grandson's body buried "in a private and decent manner, marking the spot of the interment, so that it may be known." He asks for Duralde's "cloathes, watch, papers and other effects" to be packed and shipped to him. Clay closes saying "ruthless death, has deprived me of Six affectionate daughters, all that I ever had, and has now commenced his work of destruction, with my descendents, in the second generation."
  - Henry Clay to Arthur Wells 1846 November 17, LS, 1 p. #5718-c. (Box-folder 2:89)
    In unidentified hand. Clay sends "congratulations on the recent triumph of the Whigs and it adds to my pleasure that their success has been achieved on great and vital principles of policy." He hopes that if "the Whigs are hereafter wise...there is much reason to hope that the administration of our General Government may be again brought back to a just comprehension and a faithful support of sound principles of National policy."
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to Geo[rge] Stone 1847 May 15, ALS, 1 p. #2575. (Box-folder 2:90)
    Clay thanks Stone for his "friendly letter of condolence, on the occasion of the death of my beloved son, at the battle of Buena Vista." He hopes that God will help him "ultimately to bear, with becoming resignation, the infliction which His providence has permitted."
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to W.R. Prince 1847 May 28, ALS, 1 p.; with attached blank leaf. #1665. (Box-folder 2:91)
    Clay thanks Prince for his offer to "send me next fall any tree or plant which I might select from you rich and ample collection." Clay has "as many rare shrubs plants and trees as I care about" but would be grateful if Prince would send "a half dozen choice Firs."
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to Richard Henry Wilde 1847 June 21, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. #2290, Tracy W. McGregor Library. (Box-folder 2:92)
    Clay discusses financial matters and a case to be heard by the Supreme Court.
  - Henry Clay to J.D.G. Quirk 1847 July 16, ALS, 1 p.; photocopy; location of original unknown. (Box-folder 2:93)
    Clay thanks Quirk for sending the "locket and breastpin" containing locks of Clay's son's hair. Clay says these items will be "more highly prized by us 'than rubies and diamonds.'" Clay also thanks Quirk for procuring the "splendid Coffin."
  - Henry Clay, W. Sulphur S., to P.[hilip] R. Fendall, 1847 July 30, ALS, 1 p. #2180. (Box-folder 2:94)
    Clay regrets he was unable to see Fendall "after you were so kind as to proceed to Balto. to meet me." He asks Fendall to thank Joseph Gales for his invitation, but will be unable to accept since it is "not a part of my arrangements to pass by the metropolis."
  - Henry Clay, White S. Springs 1847 July 30, ANS, 1 p. #38-115. (Box-folder 2:95)
    Clay responds to the request for an autograph from the unidentified daughter of "an admirer."
  - Henry Clay, Cape May, to Messrs. Carter, Hargrave, Cochran, Magruder, Watson, Southall and Timberlake 1847 August 17, ALS, 1 p.; with attached blank leaf and separate letter cover postmarked Philadelphia, Aug. 19. #5711. (Box-folder 2:96)
    Clay thanks the representatives of the "Commte. of Citizens of Albemarle" for their invitation to visit Charlottesville. Clay regrets that he could not attend but his travel arrangements were already fixed. The object of the "journey, moreover, was to escape from daily scenes, which constantly reminded me of a heavy domestic affliction." He closes with warm regards and thanks for their "generous sympathy."
  - Henry Clay, Cape May, to John L. Lawrence 1847 August 21, ALS, 1 p. #5828, Tracy W. McGregor Library. (Box-folder 2:97)
    Clay thanks Lawrence for "tendering the hospitality of your roof, of which I should have been very happy to avail myself, if I had visited N.Y."
  - Henry Clay, Cape Island, to Messrs. Henry White and A.I. Lewis 1847 August 21, ALS, 1 p. #1649, Tracy W. McGregor Library. (Box-folder 2:98)
    Clay thanks White and Lewis for their invitation "to partake of a public dinner" in Philadelphia on his journey to the east coast. He declines the invitation since "it would be entirely incompatible with the state of my feelings."
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to R.P. Letcher 1847 December 22, ALS, 1 p. #2933-a. (Box-folder 2:99)
    Clay asks if Letcher will be going to Washington as Clay is "called there by business."
  - Henry Clay to Harriette McIlhaney 1848 February 22, AN, 1 p.; with portion of cover laid down. #5806. (Box-folder 2:100)
    Clay sends [a lock of his hair?] [not present] and thanks Miss McIhaney for the gift for Mrs. Clay.
  - Henry Clay to William F. Wickham 1848 February 22, AN. #15753. (Box-folder 2:100a)
    Clay declines an invitation to visit.
  - Henry Clay to W.[illiam] E.[rigena] Robinson 1848 March 4, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf. #1754-b. (Box-folder 2:101)
    Clay encloses the autographs he promised [not present]. He has not seen the issue of Philadelphia Daily News mentioned by Robinson. Clay will leave for New York "Tuesday next" and shudders "in contemplation at the scenes which I shall have to pass."
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to A.D. Haslett 1848 April 14, ALS, 1 p. #6004. (Box-folder 2:102)
    Clay sends the requested lock of hair [not present] and regrets that "it is not something more worthy of your acceptance."
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to John L. Lawrence 1848 June 16, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with envelope; postmarked Lexington, Ky. Jun 17. #5828, Tracy W. McGregor Library. (Box-folder 2:103)
    "Private" in Clay's hand above salutation. Clay states that the "action of the Whig Convention did not take me altogether by surprize, although I was greatly surprized at some of the incidents attending it." He mentions his astonishment "at the course of the Ohio delegation." He says it is his "inclination, and perhaps my duty, quietly to submit to the decision of the Convention, so far as I am personally concerned. Beyond that I feel under no obligation to go." Clay says that Zachary Taylor would not have withdrawn his name were Clay nominated. Clay says "Genl. Taylor professes to be a Whig in name, but disclaims all obligations to carry our Whig principles and measures. In that respect his case differs entirely from that of Genl [William Henry] Harrison." Clay has no advice to offer his friends. He desires "all the information I can get about the Convention, its secret movements and springs." Clay closes with warm regards and mentions Abraham R. Lawrence and Charles S. Morehead.
  - George Benskin Poindexter to the Proprietors of the Richmond Whig 1848 June 25, ADLS, 2 pp. on 1 l. with attached address leaf. #2784-h. (Box-folder 2:104)
    Poindexter submits an article praising Henry Clay for publication in the Whig.
  - Henry Clay, New Orleans, to A. [Pierse] 1849 February 16, ALS, 1 p.; with attached blank leaf; Barrow; large section torn from upper center, affecting first five lines of text. #991, Tracy W. McGregor Library. (Box-folder 3:1)
    Clay thanks Pierse for his recent letters and sympathizes with the illness that kept Pierse from attending the Whig convention in Philadelphia. Clay says that the "President elect will not find himself at Washington on a bed of roses." The most important issue is the "Free soil question" which, if it should "remain unadjusted during his administration, I fear it will widen the existing breach between the South and North." Clay says that he is not surprised that Pierse wishes to go to California. "To those whose age and condition in life admit of their going there, the Country offers great inducements and attractions." Clay does not know if a governor will be appointed for California and is "unwilling to make any recommendation for that office."
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to Thomas B. Stevenson 1849 June 30, ALS, 2 pp.; photocopy, location of original unknown. #2222. (Box-folder 3:2)
    Clay thanks Stevenson for his letters and sends condolences on the death of Dr. Ennis Combs. He says that as far as he remembers, Thomas Hart Benton "was pleased with and approved all that was done to admit Missouri into the Union. And if he ever reproached me with my agency in the matter, I have forgotten it." Clay says he would "deplore the event of the Administration being thrown into the minority in the H. of R. It would be bad for them, bad for the Whig party and bad for the Country." He is apprehensive that Kentucky will not elect additional Whigs in the next election. Clay comments on the political situation in Ohio and says that Pierse's "conjectures are correct in regard to the President's feelings towards me." Clay closes by saying the cholera "still lingers with us" but he has "lost no one."
  - Henry Clay, Newport, to James V. Earle 1849 August 21, ALS, 1 p. #1754-b. (Box-folder 3:3)
    Clay replies to Earle and says he has "no expectation of being in Boston prior to my return home."
  - Henry Clay to Miss Jewell 1849 December 22, ALS, 1 p. #5601. (Box-folder 3:4)
    Clay replies to a request for an autograph.
  - Henry Clay, Washington to Conway D. Whittle, Union Level Post Office, Va 1850 January 31, ALS, 1 p.; with enclosure AD, 1 p., n.d.; with envelope, postmarked Washington, D.C. Feb. 1. #7973. (Box-folder 3:5)
    Clay encloses a draft of petition requested by Whittle. He apologizes that his "engagements will not allow" him "to attend to it ought to be" and suggests "any of the Virginia members in either house will do so with pleasure." The pension concerns a pension owed to [Whittle's father?].
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to J. Morrison Harris 1850 May 18, ALS, 1 p. #1754-b. (Box-folder 3:6)
    Clay thanks Harris for his letter informing Clay of his unanimous appointment as an honorary member of the Maryland Historical Society.
  - Henry Clay to, Washington, [Francis T.] Brooke 1850 June 11, ALS, 1 p. #6273. (Box-folder 3:7)
    Clay thanks Brooke for his invitation to visit St. Julien (near Fredericksburg, Va.) but "cannot now abandon my post, we are in the midst of the Slavery contest, and I can get no discharge until is has terminated."
  - Henry Clay, Newport, to Mr. [Daniel] Webster 1850 August 22, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; docketed. #2933. (Box-folder 3:8)
    Clay has received a letter from Millard Fillmore "in which he kindly expressed his willingness, that my son James [Brown Clay] might give the finishing stroke to the negotiation which he had conducted at Lisbon, by concluding a suitable convention, and that you had concurred in that arrangement." Clay says that his son left Lisbon on July 18 and encloses a letter from him dated July 17 [not present] that gives his itinerary. Clay says he does not know if his son "would like to return to Lisbon, which would be somewhat awkward, as under his instructions, he has closed his mission there, and new Credentials might be necessary." Clay says that he will "be entirely content with any decision you make." He closes by saying he has enclosed a letter from his son [not present] to show "what serious consequences sometimes result from the free conversations between Members of Congress, and foreign members."
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to A.[lexander] H.H. Stuart 1850 November 7, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. #345. (Box-folder 3:9)
    "Confidential" in Clay's hand above salutation. Clay thanks Stuart for his recent letter. He says the information he had received that Attorney General John J. Crittenden had "prevented the appointment" of William H. Russell "to an Indian Agency" was from Dr. William M. Gwin. Clay says if there are "well founded objections to Col. Russells appointment" he does not wish it to be made. Clay is pleased with the appointment of [James S.?] Crutchfield. Clay suggests that Secretary of the Treasury Thomas Corwin "make full enquiries" about William L. Hodge in New Orleans and Philadelphia before appointing him as Assistant. Clay says Hodge is "in bad odor" in both cities "and his appointment will prejudice the Administration in both those Cities."
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to A.[lexander] H.H. Stuart 1850 November 18, ALS, 1 p.; with attached blank leaf. #345. (Box-folder 3:10)
    "Private" in Clay's hand above salutation. Clay sends a letter from Senator George W. Jones of Iowa [not present] concerning the appointment of a post master and says "[a]lthough he is a democrat, I have a great respect and regard for him and entertain great confidence in him." Clay is sorry the William Gilliam "was not appointed to the land office in Iowa City owing, as I understood, to the interference of Mr. [Fitz Henry] Warren."
  - Henry Clay to A.H.H. Stuart [1850 November 19?], ALS, 1 p.; with envelope; postmarked Lexington, Ky., Nov. 19. #345. (Box-folder 3:11)
    Clay recommends William Gilliam "for the office of the Register of the Land Office at Iowa City."
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to Editors of the New Yorker 1850 December 17, ALS, 1 p. #1754-b. (Box-folder 3:12)
    Clay thanks the editors for the newspapers he has received from them, but regrets he cannot subscribe, his "object being, rather to lessen than increase the number of papers that I now take."
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to James S. Whitney 1851 April 23, ALS, 1 p. #3920. (Box-folder 3:13)
    Clay thanks Whitney for his election as an honorary member of the Jefferson Literary and Historical Society of Philadelphia.
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to [John M. Clay] 1852 April 30, AL (copy), 1 p.; transcription by M.W. Anderson; location of original unknown. #3417-b. (Box-folder 3:14)
    Clay sends a bill of sale [not present] for a slave, Bill Burton. He tells his son he is entitled to half the $1500 held by Wright & Price.
  - Invitation of the Clayonian Literary Society of Newark, New Jersey, for the 89th anniversary of the birth of Clay 1866 April 12, D, 1 p., addressed to W.M. Force, Esq. #3417-b. (Box-folder 3:15)
  - M.W. Anderson, Lexington, Kentucky, to W.S. Hunt 1934 September 24, ALS, 1 p. #3417-b. (Box-folder 3:16)
    Concerning the purchase of a letter by Henry Clay, 1852 April 30; see transcription above.
  - Fragment of a Pro-Whig drama concerning the election of 1836 n.d., AMs, [34] pp.; pp. 7-22, 35-50, 61-61 present. #3417-b. (Box-folder 3:17)
  - Henry Clay to William C. Johnson Monday morning, ALS, 1 p. with address leaf; docketed. #5718-c. (Box-folder 3:18)
    Clay says that he kept the letter requested by Johnson "several weeks in my pocket" intending to return it. He is now unable to find the letter and fears he might have "unintentionally destroyed it."
  - "Lines on hearing a speech from Henry Clay," by Ann Sophia Stephens n.d., AMsS, 1 p.; photocopy; original in Clifton Waller Barrett Library of American Literature. #8532-b. (Box-folder 3:19)
  - Autograph n.d., ANS, 1 p. #8641-d. (Box-folder 3:20)
    "I am with great respect, your obt. Serv."
- Series II: Photographs and Prints
  - Talbotype of Henry Clay 1850, #3417-b. (Box-folder 3:21)
  - Carte-de-visite photograph of Henry Clay n.d., #7055. (Box-folder 3:22)
    "Published by Craft & Ferry Photographers, 132 Bowery, New York."
  - Silhouette of Henry Clay 1841 March 10, Photographic copy; location of original unknown. #5231-a. (Box-folder 3:23)
  - Portrait of Henry Clay 1842, #3193. (Box-folder 3:24)
    "I have wished the good opinion of the world but I defy the most malignant of my enemies to show that I have attempted to gain it by any low or groveling acts by any mean or unworthy sacrifice by the violation of any of the obligations of honor or by a breach of any of the duties which I owed to my country." "Published by H.R. Robinson, Hoboken, New Jersey."
  - Portrait of Henry Clay 1854 (Box-folder 3:25)
    "John M. Butler & Alfred Long" Clay addressing the Senate on the omnibus bill, 1850.
  - Portrait of Henry Clay 1856, 2 copies. #2908, #8483-c. (Box-folder 3:26)
    "Martin & Johnson" Oval portrait within ornamental border, above three vignettes showing, left to right, Clay in the House of Representatives, signing the Treaty of Ghent, and at home with his family.
  - Portrait of Henry Clay 1861, #3248. (Box-folder 3:27)
    "Likeness from a portrait in the possession of his family. Johnson, Fry & Co. Publishers, New York."
  - Portrait of Henry Clay n.d., 2 copies. #10751. (Box-folder 3:28)
    "Engd. by W.G. Jackman, from a daguerreotype by Brady. N.Y. D. Appleton & Co."
  - Portrait of Henry Clay n.d., Detached from unidentified book; text on attached guard sheet: "Henry Clay photogravure after a daguerreotype by Brady." Derivative of image #10751, above. (Box-folder 3:29)
  - Portrait of Henry Clay n.d., "Engd. by W.J. Edwards from Dag. by Brady." Within ornamental border, above vignette entitled "Peace negotiations at Ghent." Not the same image as #10751, above. (Box-folder 3:30)
  - Portrait of Henry Clay n.d. (Box-folder 3:31)
    "Bureau Engraving & Printing."
  - Portrait of Henry Clay n.d., 4 copies. #2180, #10751. (Box-folder 3:32)
    "Daguerreotype by Root. Engraved by A. Sealey"
  - Portrait of Henry Clay n.d. (Box-folder 3:33)
    "Engraved by J.B. Longacre from a painting by W.J. Hubard."
  - Portrait of Henry Clay n.d. (Box-folder 3:34)
    "C. Fenderich del. Fredk. Halpin, sculp. Ptd. by Neale & Pate."
  - Portrait of Henry Clay n.d., #2908. (Box-folder 3:35)
    "Drawn & engraved from several daguerreotypes by A.H. Ritchie. Likeness principally taken from a fine daguerreotype by Messrs. Page & Beach, proprietors of the Plumbe Daguerrean Gallery, Washington."
  - Portrait of Henry Clay n.d., Photographic copy of unidentified print. (Box-folder 3:36)
  - "Henry Clay and his wife" n.d., #9860. (Box-folder 3:37)
    "Engraved by T. Johnson. After a photograph in possession of Louis E. Levy, Esq."
  - Engraving of statue of Henry Clay, New Orleans, La. 1860 April 28, Detached from Harper's Weekly.
  - Photograph of statue of Henry Clay by Thomas Ball n.d. (Box-folder 3:38)